Guide to the Thomas Howard Ruger Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Howard Ruger papers
1821-1958
1878-1907
WA MSS S-2699
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.21
(13 boxes) + 1 roll
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, printed material, and maps that document the military career and personal life of United States Army general Thomas Howard Ruger, focusing on his years in Montana, the Dakotas, and Missouri, 1879-1895. The collection contains significant documentation of the relationship between Native Americans and the United States government, especially the Lakota, Cheyenne, Kiowa, Arapaho, Crow, and Chiricahua Apache communities. Correspondence and records from Ruger's post as commander of the Department of Dakota document actions taken by United States Army personnel to track Ghost Dance practitioners (including Kicking Bear and Sitting Bull) and to quell the Ghost Dance religious movement during the Ghost Dance War, 1890-1891. The papers also contain correspondence and reports documenting Ruger's and others' reactions to the death of Sitting Bull and the Wounded Knee Massacre. Four cloth maps document geographic details of Sioux reservations in North and South Dakota, and the site of the Wounded Knee Massacre. The collection includes letters from United States Army generals William T. Sherman and Nelson A. Miles, Lakota leader Sitting Bull, United States secretaries of war William Crowinshield Endicott and Redfield Proctor, and United States president Benjamin Harrison.
Ruger, Thomas Howard, 1833-1907
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co.(Cowan's sale, 2009 June 24, lots 283, 284 and 285) on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2009.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Professional Papers, 1865-1907. II. Maps, 1890-1891. III. Personal Correspondence, 1861-1907. IV. Ruger Family Papers, 1821-1958.
Thomas Howard Ruger (1833-1907)
Thomas Howard Ruger (1833-1907) was born in Lima, New York and graduated from the United States Military Academy at West Point in 1854. He saw active duty in the United States Army during the Civil War and in the Reconstruction South, eventually rising to the rank of brigadier general. He was the superintendent of the United States Military Academy, 1871-1876, Commander of the Department of the South, 1876-1878, Commander of the District of Montana, 1879-1886, Commander of the Department of Dakota, 1886-1891, Commander of the Department of California, 1891-1894, Commander of the Military Division of the Missouri, 1894-1895, and Commander of the Department of the East, 1895-1897. Ruger was promoted to major general in 1895 and retired from the Army in 1897. Ruger died on June 3, 1907, in Stamford, Connecticut. He married Helen Lydia Moore in 1857 and they had two daughters, Helen Ruger Hay and Anna Ruger.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, printed material, and maps that document the military career and personal life of United States Army general Thomas Howard Ruger, focusing on his years in Montana, the Dakotas, and Missouri, 1879-1895. The collection contains significant documentation of the relationship between Native Americans and the United States government, especially the Lakota, Cheyenne, Kiowa, Arapaho, Crow, and Chiricahua Apache communities. Correspondence and records from Ruger's post as commander of the Department of Dakota document actions taken by United States Army personnel to track Ghost Dance practitioners (including Kicking Bear and Sitting Bull) and to quell the Ghost Dance religious movement during the Ghost Dance War, 1890-1891. The papers also contain correspondence and reports documenting Ruger's and others' reactions to the death of Sitting Bull and the Wounded Knee Massacre. Four cloth maps document geographic details of Sioux reservations in North and South Dakota, and the site of the Wounded Knee Massacre. The collection includes letters from United States Army generals William T. Sherman and Nelson A. Miles, Lakota leader Sitting Bull, United States secretaries of war William Crowinshield Endicott and Redfield Proctor, and United States president Benjamin Harrison.
The collection includes correspondence, reports, and other records documenting the Crow War of 1887, when Ruger served as the commander of the Department of Dakota. Papers from Ruger's post at the Military Division of the Missouri document the treatment of the Chiricahua Apache prisoners of war held at Fort Sill, 1894-1895. The collection contains officers' reports of armed conflicts with Native American tribes, lists of tribal leaders and Native Americans suspected of unrest, and records of Native Americans enlisting in the United States Army as scouts. There are also transcriptions of speeches by Native Americans and accounts of Native Americans' grievances against white settlers, Indian agents, and the United States government.
Other military papers document Ruger's term as president of the Military Service Institution of the United States, 1901-1907. Personal correspondence documents Ruger's family life and travels, including extensive correspondence with his wife and daughters. Family papers include the correspondence of Ruger's wife Helen Moore Ruger, daughters Helen Ruger Hay and Anna Ruger, and son-in-law Thomas A. H. Hay. Other family papers include genealogical records, wills, and correspondence relating to Ruger's family after his death.
Apache Indians; Arapaho Indians; Cheyenne Indians; Chiricahua Indians; Crow Indians; Crow Indians -- Wars; Dakota Indians; Dakota Indians -- Wars, 1890-1891; Generals -- United States; Ghost dance; Hunkpapa Indians; Indian scouts -- United States; Indians of North America -- Great Plains; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- Montana; Indians of North America -- Oklahoma; Indians of North America -- North Dakota; Indians of North America -- South Dakota; Indians of North America -- Wars -- 1866-1895; Indians of North America -- Wyoming; Lakota Indians; Lakota Indians -- Wars; Miniconjou Indians; Oglala Indians; Siksika Indians -- Montana; Wounded Knee Massacre, S.D., 1890 -- Maps; Fort Sill (Okla.); Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation (Mont.); South Dakota -- Maps; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; Maps (documents); Generals -- United States; Hay, Helen Ruger, 1859-1920; Kicking Bear, 1853-1904; Miles, Nelson Appleton, 1839-1925; Ruger, Anna, 1867-1944; Ruger, Helen Moore, 1837-1912; Ruger, Thomas Howard, 1833-1907; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Sitting Bull, 1831-1890; Military Service Institution of the United States; United States. Army. Department of California (1865-1913); United States. Army. Department of Dakota; United States. Army. Department of the East; United States. Army. District of Montana; United States. Army. Military Division of the Missouri; United States. Army ( Officers); United States Infantry and Cavalry School (1886-1901); United States. Office of Indian Affairs. Blackfeet Agency
- Professional Papers, 1865-1907; Series I; 3.55; (9 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: District of Montana Post, Department of Dakota Post, Military Division of the Missouri Post, and Other Professional Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, reports, and other papers documenting Thomas Howard Ruger's career in the United States Army, including his posts as Commander of the District of Montana, 1879-1886, Commander of the Department of Dakota, 1886-1891, Commander of the Department of California, 1891-1894, Commander of the Military Division of the Missouri, 1894-1895, and Commander of the Department of the East, 1895-1897. Includes records of the Ghost Dance War and Wounded Knee Massacre, as well as documentation of the Chiricahua Apache prisoners of war held at Fort Sill.
  - District of Montana Post, 1877-1887
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Montana Correspondence, 1877-1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes a report on Tongue River Agency, a Commission of Military Affairs survey, and correspondence documenting the construction of Fort Assinniboine.
    - Montana Notebook, 1879-1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Thomas Howard Ruger's notebook during his post as commander of the District of Montana. Includes notes on the Blackfeet Agency, lists of local Native American tribal leaders, and scouting maps of the Black Hills and Badlands. Includes autograph letters from William T. Sherman and Nelson A. Miles.
    - Officer Reports, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Montana Correspondence, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Topics include the construction of Fort Assinniboine and hostilities with Sioux tribes at Fort Belknap Agency.
    - Orders and Financial Records, 1879-1886 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Orders and Correspondence, 1879-1886 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes orders, invitations, circulars, miscellaneous correspondence, and a certificate of assay for ore mined in Montana.
    - Correspondence concerning Fort Leavenworth, 1880-1885 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Orders concerning Courts-Martial, 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Clippings and Notes, 1881-1883 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - School of Application for Infantry and Cavalry, 1882-1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes records relating to the regulations, rules, and curriculum of the school.
    - Promotion and Orders, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Records and correspondence documenting Thomas Howard Ruger's promotion to brigadier general and assignment to the Department of Dakota.
  - Department of Dakota Post, 1887-1891
    - Crow War Correspondence, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Correspondence and memoranda documenting the Crow War of 1887. Includes information about Crow camps during the conflict and Crow leaders such as Deaf Bull, Crazy Head, and Sword Bearer.
    - Crow War Clippings, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Crow War Correspondence, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes correspondence relating to the Crow War, reports of military strategy and troop movements during the Crow War, a list of Crow leaders and families involved in the war, and a copy of a speech by Crow leaders Plenty Coups and Pretty Eagle.
    - Crow War Officer Reports, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence concerning Crow, Cheyenne, and Sioux Tribes, 1887-1890 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Includes correspondence concerning government and intertribal relations with Crow, Cheyenne, and Sioux tribes during and after the Crow War. Includes correspondence concerning Ruger's proposal that Native Americans enlist in the United States Army as scouts.
    - Special Orders, 1888-1891 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Records documenting Thomas Howard Ruger's special orders from United States secretary of war Redfield Proctor and United States president Benjamin Harrison. Topics include the Cheyenne Commission and courts of inquiry.
    - Yellowstone Correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Correspondence concerning the United States Army's management of Yellowstone Park, including the presence of troops in Yellowstone.
    - Ghost Dance War Correspondence, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Correspondence concerning the Ghost Dance movement, including the history of the movement, Thomas Howard Ruger's reports of a visit to Standing Rock Agency, the United States government's assessment of the origins and prevalence of the movement, and a list of Native American leaders of the movement. Includes typescript copies of letters from United States president Benjamin Harrison and Lakota leader Sitting Bull.
    - Ghost Dance War Correspondence, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Correspondence concerning the Ghost Dance War, particularly relating to Sitting Bull. Includes orders for Sitting Bull's arrest, correspondence concerning the movements of United States troops and Sitting Bull in December 1890, and accounts of Sitting Bull's death. Also includes a list of Lakota tribal leaders, the locations of their camps, and the number of people in their bands.
    - Ghost Dance War correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Contains correspondence and reports concerning the Ghost Dance War, written and received during Thomas Howard Ruger's post at the Department of California.
    - Wounded Knee Reports and Correspondence, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Reports and correspondence from multiple United States Army officers in the wake of the Wounded Knee Massacre. Includes accounts of troop movements and orders in the days before the massacre on December 29, 1890. Includes conflicting accounts and a dispute between two officers about the surrender and imprisonment of the Lakota at Fort Sully.
    - Wounded Knee Reports, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Contains reports documenting United States military action before and after the Wounded Knee Massacre, including an officer's report and a report about an officer who died during the campaign.
    - Dakota Correspondence, 1888-1891 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Topics include infantry drill regulations, the division of Sioux agencies into multiple reservations, and Thomas Howard Ruger's comments on proposed changes to the officer promotion system of the United States Army. Includes letters from United States secretaries of war Redfield Proctor and William Crowninshield Endicott.
    - Dakota Correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Topics include the appointment of a commander for the Infantry and Cavalry School of Application and Thomas Howard Ruger's appointment to command the Military Division of the Pacific and the Department of California.
    - Scrapbook of Clippings about the Ghost Dance War, 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Military Division of the Missouri Post, 1894-1895
    - Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency Crimes and Grievances, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      Includes a list of grievances raised by the Native Americans of Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency against white settlers and an account of crimes committed by white settlers and Native Americans at Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency.
    - Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency Reports, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Reports about the population, resources, land, and rations of Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency.
    - Correspondence concerning Apache Prisoners of War at Fort Sill, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Correspondence concerning several hundred Chiricahua Apache prisoners of war, including their transportation to Fort Sill and the United States government's provisions for them, including shelter, food, clothing, tools, and education for the children. Includes letters from Nelson A. Miles.
    - Correspondence concerning Kiowa, Comanche, and Apache near Fort Sill, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Correspondence concerning Apache, Kiowa, and Comanche tribes near Fort Sill, including recommendations for an increased Indian police force.
    - Indian Territory Correspondence, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Includes reports on relations between Native Americans and white settlers in Oklahoma and correspondence concerning the Kiowa, Comanche, Cheyenne, Arapaho, and Wichita tribes. Includes a memorandum entitled "In Regard to the Troubles in the Indian Territory" and a list of the tribes, Native American population, and Indian agents of every Native American reservation in the Military Division of the Missouri.
    - Military Division of the Missouri Orders and Correspondence, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Orders and general correspondence during Thomas Howard Ruger's post at the Military Division of the Missouri. Topics include wells at Fort Reno and Thomas Howard Ruger's promotion to major general.
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      Three newspaper clippings about the Chickasaw tribe and train robberies.
  - Other Professional Papers, 1865-1907
    Includes correspondence, reports, and financial records from Thomas Howard Ruger's other military posts, including his service during the Civil War, 1864-1865, the Department of the South, 1876-1878, the Department of California, 1890-1891, and the Department of the East, 1895-1897. Includes miscellaneous professional papers, orders, and correspondence, including invitations, circulars, and correspondence concerning Ruger's retirement from the United States Army.
    - Orders, 1865-1866 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Financial Records, 1864-1894 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      Includes receipts, bills, checks, financial correspondence, and quartermaster records.
    - Department of the South Orders and Correspondence, 1876-1878 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Department of California Orders and Correspondence, 1891-1895 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      Topics include drill regulations, financial records, invitations, and the boundary between Fort Canby and Cape Disappointment.
    - Department of California Correspondence, 1892-1894 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      Topics include Thomas Howard Ruger's command of the Department of the Columbia and the possibility of war with Great Britain in 1892.
    - Department of California Reports and Correspondence, 1893-1894 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      Topics include the appointment of messengers, invitations, firing practice, and reports on infantry regulations.
    - Correspondence, 1894-1895 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      Includes invitations and correspondence concerning the United States Army Signal Corps.
    - Letters of Congratulations on Promotion to Major General, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 41-43)
    - Letters of Congratulations on Promotion to Major General, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 44-45)
    - Correspondence concerning a Confederate Memorial in Chicago, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Invitations and Circulars, 1895-1903 (Box 6, Folder 47-51)
    - Department of the East Orders and Correspondence, 1895-1896 (Box 6, Folder 52-53)
      Topics include infantry drills, machine gun regulations, the appointment of messengers and clerks, and invitations.
    - Correspondence concerning Chinese Ambassador Li Hongzhang's Visit to the United States, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 54-56)
    - Preparations for War with Great Britain, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 57-58)
      Correspondence, reports, and orders concerning preparations for a possible war with Great Britain during the Venezuelan Crisis of 1895-1896.
    - Invitations, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - New York Chief of Police Correspondence, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 60)
      Correspondence concerning Mayor of New York City William Lafayette Strong's offer to appoint Thomas Howard Ruger as the chief of police for New York City.
    - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 61)
      Contents include invitations, correspondence concerning Thomas Howard Ruger's international travel, and Ruger's passport.
    - Invitations and Circulars, 1897-1901 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Retirement Orders and Congratulations, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Invitations and Professional Organizations, 1898 (Box 8, Folder 64)
      Includes invitations and nominations from the American Institute of Civics and the American Forestry Association.
    - Correspondence, 1898 (Box 8, Folder 65)
      Topics include the Spanish-American War, the use of shoulder rifles in the United States Army, and Thomas Howard Ruger's proposal that retired Army officers return to active duty during the Spanish-American War.
    - Military Service Institution Correspondence, 1899-1907 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Society of the Army of Ohio Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Correspondence and Invitations, 1904-1907 (Box 8, Folder 68-69)
    - Receipts, 1905-1907 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Chinese Painting on Silk Scroll, circa 1896 (Box 9)
      Most likely a diplomatic gift from Chinese ambassador Li Hongzhang's visit to the United States in 1896.
- Maps, 1890-1891; Series II; 4; (1 roll)
  Four cyanotype cloth maps documenting United States Army forts and Native American reservations during the Ghost Dance War and Wounded Knee Massacre, 1890-1891.
  - Map of Country Comprising Forts Meade, Custer, Keogh, and McKenney, 1890 (Box Roll 10)
  - Map of Country Comprising the Sioux Indian Reservations in North and South Dakota, 1890 (Box Roll 10)
  - Scene of the Fight with Big Foot's Band (2 copies), 1891 (Box Roll 10)
- Personal Correspondence, 1861-1907; Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Thomas Howard Ruger's personal correspondence, primarily with his wife Helen Moore Ruger and daughters Helen Ruger Hay and Anna Ruger. Other correspondents include Ruger's father, Thomas Jefferson Ruger; brother, William Ruger; and sisters, Adelaide Ruger Dunbar and Cornelia Ruger Pease.
  - Dunbar, Adelaide Ruger, 1878 (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Hay, Helen Ruger, 1879-1907 (Box 11, Folder 72)
  - Heaston, William, 1884 (Box 11, Folder 73)
  - Pease, Cornelia Ruger, circa 1883 (Box 11, Folder 74)
  - Pease, John J. R., 1879-1882 (Box 11, Folder 75)
  - Roode, John, 1883 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - Ruger, Anna, 1879-1884 (Box 11, Folder 77-78)
  - Ruger, Eliza, 1883 (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - Ruger, Frank, 1877 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - Ruger, Helen Moore, 1879 (Box 11, Folder 81-82)
  - Ruger, Helen Moore, 1882-1883 (Box 11, Folder 83-84)
  - Ruger, Helen Moore, 1884 (Box 12, Folder 85-87)
  - Ruger, Thomas Howard, Letters to Helen Ruger Hay, 1882-1888 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Ruger, Thomas Howard, Letters to Anna Ruger, 1885-1900 (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - Ruger, Thomas Howard, Letters to Helen Moore Ruger, 1861-1889 (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Ruger, Thomas Howard, Letters to Helen Moore Ruger, 1895-1902 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Ruger, Thomas Jefferson, 1868-1870 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - Ruger, William, 1877-1906 (Box 12, Folder 93)
  - Envelopes, 1879-1884 (Box 13, Folder 94)
- Ruger Family Papers, 1821-1958; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Correspondence, wills, and other papers documenting the Ruger, Hay, Dickinson, and Wilson families in Ireland, England, and the United States. Includes Thomas Howard Ruger and Helen Moore Ruger's marriage certificate and letters of condolence after Thomas Howard Ruger's death in 1907.
  - Dickinson, Annie Wilson Hay, Will and Probate, 1941-1958 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - Hay, Helen Ruger, Correspondence, 1881-1892 (Box 13, Folder 96-97)
  - Hay, Helen Ruger and Thomas A. H. Hay, Marriage Certificate and Correspondence, 1881-1909 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - Hay, Thomas A. H., Correspondence, 1879 (Box 13, Folder 99)
  - Ruger, Anna, Correspondence, 1881-1927 (Box 13, Folder 100-101)
  - Ruger, Anna, European Tour Diaries, 1895 (Box 13, Folder 102-103)
  - Ruger, Helen Moore and Thomas Howard Ruger, Marriage Certificate, 1857 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Ruger, Helen Moore, Correspondence, 1879-1911 (Box 14, Folder 105-108)
  - Ruger, Maria Hutchins, Letter, 1844 (Box 14, Folder 109)
  - Wilson Family Papers, 1829-1899 (Box 14, Folder 110)
    Deeds, indentures, correspondence, and other papers concerning John Wilson (1803-1840), Alexander Wilson (1809-1884), and Jacob B. Odenwelder (1809-1884).
  - Wilson, Alexander, United States Naturalization Certificate, 1835 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  - Wilson, Alexander and James Wilson, Correspondence, 1821-1845 (Box 14, Folder 112-113)